我以為係。
亦至明言。
條例草案。
獲得通過。
審議程序受阻。
有限合夥基金條例草案。
喺舊年嘅十月十八日，已經喺立法會進行首讀。
但係，因為內務委員會遲遲未能夠選出主席。
《節令度條例草案》今日先能夠再上立法會恢復議讀。
條例草案係冇議員要求成立法案委員會審審議。
都係為咗落實行政長官喺二零一八年施政報告裏邊所建議。
藉住税務寬減支持同埋提升高增值海運服務嘅發展。
我發言咧係支持二零一九年税務修訂與保險有關嘅業務嘅利得税寬減條例草案。
同上個月初喺立法會通過嘅《二零二零年税務修訂船泊租任税務寬減條例草案》。
政府法案本會恢復2019年税務修訂與保險有關嘅業務嘅利得税寬減條例草案嘅二讀辯論，是否有議員想發言？
嚟提升香港嘅競爭力。
係倫敦境外最大嘅服務羣組。
海事保險係海運服務重要嘅一環。
三十四間係海外註冊嘅公司。
當中係有五十四間係香港嘅註冊公司。
證明大家都係認同香港係有必要推出税務優惠。
包括一啲喺香港開設分公司嘅國際大型保險企業。
除此之外，中國船東互保協會喺香港亦都設有辦事處。
船東係可以有效噉樣管理各種複雜嘅風險同埋責任事宜。
提供船體同埋機械、船東責任以及貨物運輸等嘅保險。
香港係擁有歷史悠久嘅海運服務，具備咗發展為海事保險中心嘅條件。
現時，本港共有八十八間喺香港獲授權承保船殼保險嘅公司。
國際保障及離常組織嘅十三個成員協會當中，就有十二個喺香港提供服務。
至於淨保費，二零一九年亦都較二零一八年增加咗百分之六。海事保險業務喺香港係不斷噉樣擴展。
二零一九年涉及呢個船舶業務承保嘅無保費就達到二十七億港元，較二零一八年增加咗一成。
自由黨係支持條例組案，並希望及早通過，以吸引更多海外保險業務嚟香港，推動香港嘅海運業務嘅發展。
香港係全球第四大嘅船泊註冊處。
國際海上保險聯盟簡稱IUMI。
喺香港購買嘅海上保險保費佔全球總額百不足百分之一。
隨住經濟活動東移，海上保險市場亦都逐漸由歐洲轉移到亞洲。
海事保險業務持續增長，一啲保險書樓相繼推出税務優惠嚟提升競爭力。
而亞洲嘅比率咧，就由二零一七年嘅百分之二十九點二上升到二零一八年嘅百分之三十點七。
顯然咧喺發展海事保險係有一定嘅空間，但係政府喺促進海事保險發展方面嘅力度就略嫌不足。
不單止係突顯咗海事保險東移，亦都證明香港喺區內嘅海運保險業務有舉足輕重嘅角色。
咁為咗促進海事保險嘅發展咧，政府係需要推出措施，製造有利嘅海事保險發展嘅營運環境。
喺二零一六年決定喺香港設立亞洲區嘅中心，作為聯盟喺德國總部以外嘅首個分支嘅組織。
歐洲所佔嘅市場比率就由二零一七年嘅百分之四十九點二下降至到二零一八年嘅百分之四十六點四。
新加坡喺二零一六年已經向城堡船體保險及海上強制責任保險嘅公司提供百分之十嘅優惠税率。
根據國際海上保險聯盟喺二零一九年九月嘅公佈，二零一八年全球海上保險收入為二百八十九億美元。
而瑞士亦都喺今年嘅一月一日起，將有關税率由平均百分之十七點零六減為百分之十二至到百分之十四。
英國就喺今年嘅四誒四月一日起，將公司税嘅税率由百分之十九減到百分之十七，可見透過税務優惠，直意在海事保險業務方面分一杯羹，係大勢所趨。
截至到二零一九年嘅一月一號，香港註冊嘅船泊數目達到二千七百零一艘，佔全球船泊總噸位百分之九。但係根據香港金融發展局喺二零一七年發表有關海事保險嘅報告裏邊指出。
香港仲係欠缺相關嘅專業人才。
因此，特區政府提出今日嘅條例草案。
係有利發展為區內主要嘅爭議解決中心之一。
以及三直接保險人嘅特定一般保險業務。
而特定一般保險業務就涵涵蓋咗城保海事相關風險嘅保險。
但係，如果要做大海事保險及其他相關海事海事事務嘅餅咧？
嘅保險經紀業務，二直接保險人嘅所有一般再保險業務。
除咗提及可透過香港嘅仲裁裁決做船同埋船樁買賣嘅交易。
即上述提及嘅船體同埋機械保險、貨物保險以及船東責任保險。
船殼管理同埋船東保障及賠償等嘅事宜上嘅爭議，仲可以發展為保險嘅合約仲裁中心。
而紐約公約適用於香港，喺香港所作出嘅仲裁裁決，更加可以喺超過一百五十個替約國去執行。
雖然香港喺二零一四年成立咗海運及空運人才培訓基金，以資助海運同埋航空界從業員接受基金核准嘅培訓以及考試。
主席，正如我喺上次就船舶租任税務減寬減條例草案發言時提及，香港喺一國兩制之下，法律制度係以普通法為依歸，由成文法作補充。
希望税務寬減嘅措施落實之後，喺促進國際海上保險公司以及保險經紀喺香港開展業務嘅同時，亦都能夠吸引海外相關嘅人才嚟香港工作。
措施落實之後，海事保險業務成本將得以下降，相信係有助吸引更多國際海上保險公司及保險經紀喺香港開展佢哋嘅業務，嚟促進香港海事保險業務嘅發展。
當中係包括將寬減利得税百分之五十，即係八點二五個percent嘅利得税税率嘅措施，係由現時只限於香港嘅專屬自保保險業務同埋專業再保險人嘅再保險業務擴展到去其他三個範疇，包括一特定。
香港應該加強海事保險嘅發展。
目的係推廣香港海運及海運相關嘅服務行業。
因此咧，政府係必須推出更多提升海事服務競爭力嘅措施。
雖然特區政府喺二零一六年成立咗現時嘅香港海運港口局。
最後，我再不厭其煩噉樣重申，全球貨運係有大概八成係循水路運輸嘅。
進一步提升香港作為海運服務嘅樞紐，鞏固香港為國際海運中心嘅地位。
倘若本港嘅海事羣能夠做大做強，自然能夠吸引更多嘅船東以及國際航運業。
除咗船泊保險之外，仲有船泊管理、船泊經紀以及租船、船泊融資、海運仲裁等等。
香港係國際領先嘅海運中心。現時香港有超過八百多家公司提供一係列優質嘅海運服務。
根據政府統計處嘅資料咧，船東以及船泊營運者喺二零一八年嘅業務收益為八百四十二億港元。
誒經營者咧係落户香港，繼而就將香港嘅高增值海運服務做大，進一步推動香港嘅海運業嘅發展。
可見航運業嘅發展係極具潛力，兵家必爭之地，各國都係積極噉樣吸納船公司以及國際貨主落户。
但係，海運港口局始終係政府當局嘅一個諮詢機構，係難以主動推動有利海運及港口業務發展嘅政策。
政府應該向內地爭取香港成為解決一帶一路建設專案投資、商業爭議以及海事保險糾紛等嘅指定仲裁中心。
如果有海事保險糾紛，香港亦都有專家處理，有豐富嘅仲裁調解經驗。而國家嘅一帶一路倡議就為海運業同埋保險業帶嚟龐大嘅機遇。
較二零一七年增加咗百分之十二點八，而業務增加嘅價值以及人均增加價值就較二零一七年分別上升咗百分之一百零三以及百分之六十一。
嗯。
motor vehicle damage risk。
the bill the structure of the bill is quite
first of all， general reinsurance business of direct insurers。
profits tax concessions for insurance related business bill 2019.
Currently, there are 17 classes of general insurance businesses.
主席本人緊支持支持條例草案恢復議路。梁繼昌議員。
這些exception包括健康風險、抵押貸款保證風險。
Mr President, today we're talking about the resumption of the second reading of the Inland Revenue Amendment.
however，this bill only extends the concessionary tax rate to all of them except。
五個類別，意味著這些類別的保險業務不會吸引，折扣利率。
secondly， and which is the most important concession made in this bill is the selected general insurance business of direct insurers.
simple. First of all, the profits tax rate, the standard profits tax rate of sixteen point five percent, will be reduced to half to.
長遠嚟講咧，希望政府係積極考慮成立香港海運港口管理局，一個有實權嘅法定機構，更加有效咁推動香港嘅海運同埋港口業，提升香港嘅國際航運中心嘅地位。
now the reason for the proposal of this bill is to increase our competitiveness against other major insurance centre internationally, including London, Switzerland and other countries.
now the purpose of the bill is to give profits tax concession to certain activities carried out by general insurance business of and other businesses including insurance brokerage and also certain general reinsurance business of direct insurers.
啊！
No.
however。
looking at the five.
employees compensation liability.
and owners, corporation, third party liability.
The government has given us the explanation that these.
however，I I back to divers because。
我 think in deciding why these categories of insurance businesses are excluded.
perhaps i i i also want to raise a point generally is that the public would be concerned why we should benefit the insurance sector
有 Quite a number of wealthy people from the Asian countries or from part of the mainland, they will come to Hong Kong to get insurance coverage.
General insurance business and the selected insurance brokerage business is that other countries are doing that, and we could be losing out. We are not going to do so.
categories of insurance business are merely more domestically risk. They are contained within the Hong Kong boundary. They have no international dimension.
accepted categories the health risk I think quite a lot of people come to Hong Kong to get health insurance because we are a service oriented city we do provide first class professional services including insurance services.
And I hope if you got another chance to reconsider or to amend this bill, please would you take into consideration health risk? Because I do think apart from domestic, you know, people in Hong Kong living in Hong Kong will take those kinds of insurance.
now this is given under the background that the professional reinsurance business has already been enjoying a fifty percent concessionary tax rate. now of course the main reason why we are giving special concessions to the
hedge funds。
to give.
The secretary.
要考慮這條條例 favourably。
會比更多，than we are collecting.
abate the concessionary tax rate we have been given.
to insurance sectors, to the leasing, you know industries etc.
在一般保險 sector，兩或三年下，個路，after the bill is passed。
I think stepping back and to assess the effectiveness and the economic impact of this concession.
And the formula, the only formula which the government has always been using is to use a half profits tax rate, which is eight point two five percent.
now and talking about how the government has been giving out tax concessions to various sectors, as we all know, we've been giving out tax concessions to
And only if this is the case that you know, we will be happy to support this bill. And of course, we have no crystal ball at this moment, and we would like you know.
Well, we have to take a snapshot, say two or three years later, to look at the business generated by this sector and also the tax revenue generated by these sectors. And I all often and always would ask.
so that we know that we are not losing too much of our revenue, and we also would like to see that, say three or four years down the road, the revenue, the total revenue, generated from these sectors.
An economic assessment, say three years down the road after this bill has been passed, and I would also like the secretary to give a more detailed report at the financial affairs panel.
But as a responsible legislator, and I hope I can continue to monitor the government, and I would like the government to undertake that they would come back to give an economic account of the growth or the change.
and indeed.
Mr Secretary, using.
We should be more innovative in giving out our tax concessions.
As competition grows.
If we are using eight point two five percent, then it will be good enough.
Now apart from using 8.25%，have you consider?
now the reason I mention is that you you can't really say.
Now，however，I，I，don't，think，this，must，be，necessarily，be，the，case，because。
day by day and our neighbouring countries and even international scene is so competitive.
because you know that some countries, well, needless to say, Singapore can come up with very innovative measures.
Coming up on my list, of course, would be the family office business. We've been talking about it for the past five, six years.
and surprisingly, some of these rates could be far, you know, below our half rate, even our half rate.
Their measures need not be contained in the legislation because they always like to use concessionary rate case by case basis.
一一quarter rate，meaning 4.125，或even a one tenth rate，meaning a 1.65% of tax rate。
所以， for some sectors, if in the future if the government would like to enhance the competitiveness of certain sectors, you may consider the four point one two five or even the one point six five percent rate.
I think in the future there is an urgent task, of course, for for the government to review which other sectors. Of course, I'm talking about the financial services sector because obviously the secretary is in charge of this sector. That these rates should apply.
啊！
now all these.
Now.
capital profits。
although we are not taxing any.
要管理投資組合的這些私人股權基金。
Some people not paying tax at all. If there are there are activities.
capital for for for the ship leasing business and all that.
for the investment management business， I think。
being conducted in Hong Kong, and they earn some of the profits in Hong Kong.
And I do understand that the government will be launching a consultation paper very soon.
coupled with the recent limited partnership fund bill, which has just been passed.
We are also considering the taxation of another very, you know, competitive business—the investment management business—in which I think you need the manager.
how to tax carried interest of course is one of the topics which been in discussion by the professionals for the past ten years and we don't seem to have a very clear cut case of how to tax them and of course some of these managers may be dodging not paying any tax at all.
Mr Chairman, I think the whole financial services sector is one integrated market. You just can't segregate out say this is the general insurance sector, because it also affects you know the transport sector, the leasing, the financial market, which.
and I don't know the direction of the consultation, but of course there are people in the financial service sector which say, well, we don't want any tax at all, we do not want to pay any tax. But as a responsible government, you need to tell the people here in Hong Kong why there should be.
But.
on the。
no matter how hard we try.
no matter how we are going to innovate.
on the port, the physical port facilities.
transport sector or the the
In twenty years' time, we'll be losing out if we are going still concentrating.
very good port facilities, container port facilities in Japan and in Singapore.
to continue to struggle with the airport facilities because I do think in the long run.
and the mainland, which are our competitors, and also we have.
我 do 覺得香港會 be 在 很 靠 近 的 未來。
If we are going to develop into a shipping centre, I would think we are going to provide a first-class professional services only and not.
How Hong Kong is going to evolve? Because the general insurance business and the shipping sector are generally go going hand in hand.
now the first foremost consideration about the shipping hub or the shipping business is that land is very scarce in Hong Kong.
Not all of these profits are capital profits. So if you are going to devise a very simple formula for taxing carried interest, I would urge you to think about the one point six five percent rate, which I do think a lot of manager will find it very attractive and palatable.
developing towards the model of London, because of of course we do have a very sizeable container port, but the ranking of this container port is dropping because our cost is high, and there are a lot of better, bigger and automated ports.
to release.
喺嚟，下兩兩個幾廿年。
back to society.
insurance，arbitration。
and other types of financing, and we have.
The port facilities, the land, especially the land.
professional services in relating to shipping. No matter it is leasing.
Of course, we cannot, as an international city.
Of other big container port cities in terms of physical facilities.
We need to have some port container port facilities, and that's all what we need to contend about.
and I think it would be better to make sense to make make bigger sense if we just concentrate on providing.
我認為政府應該有 vision，因為我們簡直不能夠與成本結構和規模競爭。
work with thou, port facilitative of some sort, but we are not going to squeeze it onto the leak table. We do not need to. We do not need to be even a top ten.
whether they will be used for housing other high-value-added industries, no matter to be used for public housing, private housing, commercial buildings or otherwise.
我 do appreciate that this is not the portfolio of the secretary, but I do hope that the secretary can bring back this message to the financial secretary and also to the chief executive. If we are going to have a vision for Hong Kong in the next two or three decades.
主席，我認為我會給予支持，到重温第二讀，和第三讀，這個法案。如果秘書處可以承諾，向財政事務小組報告，這個法案的經濟影響，幾年後。謝謝。
多謝。
嚟講咧。
周浩鼎源。
有少少奇怪，因為。
都係有一啲嘅意見想表達嘅。
啊！主席，今次呢一個嘅條例咧，係主要就係集中喺呢一個嘅利得税嘅寬減，對於嘅保險嘅業務。咁而家咧，香港嘅保險業務嚟講咧，當然我哋係歡迎政府咧係順應一個最近嘅安排。無論我哋過去見到嘅飛機租任嘅誒。
利得税嘅寬減，或者係呢一個船舶租任嘅税務嘅寬減，呢啲都係相信支援翻我哋本地呢一個嘅產業咧。希望透過税務嘅寬減咧，增強嗰個競爭力。咁所以呢個當然我哋係會歡迎嘅。不過咧，我都想喺度咧係指出咧，今次嘅條例咧，誒，我都。
誒第一咧就係話，我哋留意到今次咧嗰個税務嘅寬減咧，誒主要佢都係有講明就係誒再保險一般再保險嘅業務啦，同埋一般保險嘅業務。噉我哋集中講一講一般保險嗰個業務嘅，因為一般保險嗰個業務嚟講咧，我哋見到咧有幾個範疇，其
就係剔除咗嘅，包括健康保險啦、誒按揭擔保保險啦，同埋僱員補償誒嘅方面嘅嗰個責任嗰個保險啦。呢幾種嘅保險業務咧，一般保險嘅業務咧，今次係唔覆蓋喺呢一個減税嘅安排上面。咁其實咧呢樣嘢咧，就令我覺得。
以健康保險為例啦，都係一個比較龐大嘅誒市場。咁但係點解又唔能夠將嗰個減税嘅優惠咧係覆蓋埋落去咧？亦都係多幫助嗰啲業界嘅從業員嚇，相信都會對佢哋有幫助一樣事情。誒推出嘅產品更加有吸引力噉。
做大塊餅，何樂而不為咧？咁點解又唔要將呢幾個嘅範疇，特別係健康保險呢啲咁普遍嘅，能夠納入埋去，噉啊可以令到我哋嘅保險從業員咧又有個多啲嘅得益同埋幫助。另一個問題咧，我都想指出咧，就係今次嘅嗰個優惠裏面嚟。
税務嘅寬減嘅優惠嚟講咧，係又並冇去覆蓋人壽保險嘅啊。當然，大家知道人壽保險亦都係一個好大嘅範疇啦。咁其實如果你能夠做到一啲嘅優惠畀呢一個嘅產業減税，咁當然又係一個更加好嘅優惠嘅產品，咁又係可以幫到啲從業員。
主席喺最近呢段時間咧，我哋需知道咧，其實保險業嘅從業員，我亦都有去接洽，我亦都知道佢哋其實呢一段時間咧係已經承受緊行業嘅寒冬，因為兩地之間嘅往來，因為疫情係停曬。過去咧有好多嘅內地嘅朋友咧係落嚟誒香港購買嗰個保險。
咁但係而家呢段時間咧，完全係停曬保險業嘅好多嘅從業員咧，呢一段時間咧係好難捱嘅。咁所以咧喺未來，我哋期待當然我哋係期待啦嚇，疫情過去，當啊大家可以恢復翻兩地往來嘅時候，點樣能夠可以照顧到呢啲保險業嘅從業員嘅佢哋，無論係生計或者佢哋。
整個嘅行業嘅發展咧，呢個都係重要嘅課題。主席，我只係想講翻咧，就係誒人壽保險今次係冇覆蓋嘅。我瞭解到噉，如果人壽保險咧，而家睇翻根據保監局嘅行業數據咧，以保費嚟講咧，人壽保險同一般保險嗰個佔嘅比例咧，係達。
到九比一嘅嚇，噉我哋見到咧，即係話誒好多嘅市場比例誒比誒百分比係集中咗喺人壽保險嗰度，一般保險咧淨係佔十分一啫。咁當然我哋都希望能夠有啲打雲巡翻一啲嘅，我哋都希望能夠谷翻大一般保險嘅。
保險從業員呢方面嘅要求，主席本人緊以陳詞。
現在宣佈休會，本會喺二零二零年七月十五日星期三上午十一時召開。
咁不過喺個銀嘅另一邊，我哋就睇到咧，人壽保險的而且確喺市場佔有額係咁大嘅時候，有咁多嘅從業員係從事緊買賣人壽保險嘅推銷嘅時候，點解唔能夠可以畀佢哋再進一步有一啲嘅啊所謂嘅税務嘅優惠，導致到佢哋嗰個產品？
更有競爭力，又可以令佢哋更加好咁做大塊餅咧。呢個都係幫到我哋香港嘅從業員嘅。誒主席亦都喺呢一度咧，誒都重新表達一個好簡單嘅意見，就係我哋都約見之前，因為都約見過局方去講呢一條嘅誒法例噉，因為呢條法例本身係冇法案委員會啦，噉我都約見局方都。
同佢哋表達，今日好簡單，只係講咧，希望佢哋除咗喺呢個税務嘅優惠去幫助保險業嘅發展之外咧，唔好忘記我哋香港嘅保險業從業員係希望局方繼續去推進大灣區裏面個保險業嘅發展。首先嘅就係誒大灣區裏面嗰個嘅規劃綱要。
講咗可以畀機動車嘅保險啊，係可以開始去推進去處理嘅。同埋，另外一個就係售後服務喺大灣區嗰度開展呢個咧，都係幫我哋香港保險嘅從業員開拓嗰個嘅市場。希望咧各方聽到我呢方面嘅聲音，稍後咧都可以咧係適切咁去跟進誒。